MICHAEL R. DAVIS, I.O.M.

(317) 519-5392 Michael@GaugeResearch.com Professional Websites: <u>LinkedIn</u>
Website Porti

Website Portfolio
Tableau Public

DATA AND IT CONSULTANT / CUSTOMER ACCOUNT MANAGER

Senior business executive who leads business and government clients and connects the decision-making needs of leaders, executives, and stakeholders to better informed data analysis. Recognized for initiative and leadership in directing clients, customers, and businesses with a collaborative research-based, data-driven analytics approach to solve tough problems for clients. Active TS/SCI clearance.

CAREER EXPERIENCE

Engagement Manager - Resultant

Indianapolis, IN (2021 – present)

Serves as the sole point of contact for clients and works with them to acquire a full understanding of their business, technologies, and key resources across all levels of the organization to solve complex technology projects. Projects range from system transitions, data management projects, and product services. Acts as an advocate for the client, and identifies solutions, builds teams, and successfully delivers projects. Experience highlights include the following:

- Leads a strategic government account with Indiana Department of Education to build a Graduates
 Prepared to Succeed custom web application with a Power BI dashboard using statewide longitudinal data covering seventeen key metrics evaluating the state, schools, and individual students.
- Leads a strategic government account with the Indiana Management Performance Hub to analyze data and find solutions to the opioid crisis.
- Led a team to create a "pilot hiring analysis tool" for an airline company to project future shortfalls in the number of pilots available to fly routes.
- Manages internal finances and business development activities for my clients (\$7.02M portfolio).
- Performs contract management for associated accounts.
- Manages client capital and client need forecasting.

Owner and President - Gauge Research

Indianapolis, IN (2007 – 2021)

Owned and operated a consulting firm serving businesses in data/business analytics, public opinion research, demographic analysis, marketing, and organizational management. Highlights include:

- Collected precinct level election results from all 50 states for multiple races over several election cycles for a large statewide association. Standardized data and added U.S. Census demographic data through an API to conduct election analysis, identify trends, and create maps and Tableau visualizations.
- For a multi-state news organization, I extract, clean, digest, standardize, and create data entry forms and Tableau visualizations from large amounts of gaming data.

President and CEO - Enterprise Washington

Bellevue, WA (2013 – 2017)

- Led the state's preeminent business association for grassroots advocacy, election research, marketing analytics, and independent expenditure campaigns.
- Led The Business Institute of Washington, Washington Voter Research, and multiple PACs.
- Created a statewide database of 7 million residents with 4,000 data points per person with extensive issue and audience modeling based on consumer data, demographics, and social media use.
- Created Washington Voter Research to conduct survey research and organize field operations team.

Senior Vice President – BIPAC

Washington, D.C. (2010 – 2013)

- Served on senior management team of independent, bipartisan membership organization.
- Directed all activities related to the elections division and managing nine team members.
- Conducted first-ever nationwide ad buyout of YouTube by a political candidate or organization.
- Led the development of building a nationwide database of over 200 million individuals to utilize in digital marketing and advocacy campaigns.

Vice President-Political Affairs – Indiana Chamber of Commerce

Indianapolis, IN (2004 – 2010)

- Served on senior management team with 50 staff for the state's leading pro-business advocacy organization with over 26,000 members and customers.
- Ran all activities related to one of the country's largest state or local chamber of commerce PACs,
 Indiana Business for Responsive Government (IBRG), and its five-person team.
- Prepared autonomous departmental budgets totaling \$2M.
- Launched the online *Indiana Prosperity Project* to educate citizens on elections and business issues.

Additional personal data analytics and visualization projects can be viewed on my <u>Tableau Public Page</u> and on my <u>Professional Website Portfolio</u> I created. Subjects include COVID-19, Indy 500, home sales, earthquakes, election results, women leadership, weather, and honeybees.

EDUCATION & PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATES

- TS/SCI cleared
- Data Analytics and Visualization Executive Education Certificate Butler University, Indianapolis, IN
- Visual Analytics with Tableau Certificate, Essential Design Principles for Tableau Certificate, and Fundamentals of Visualization with Tableau Certificate - University of California, Davis, Davis, CA
- Customer Analytics Certificate The University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA
- Bachelor of Arts, Political Science; Minor: Economics Indiana University, Bloomington, IN
- Professional certificate in Nonprofit Organizational Management
 U.S. Chamber of Commerce Institute for Organization Management (I.O.M.)
- Board Member and Treasurer for Circular Indiana

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, JSON, JavaScript

Data Visualization: Tableau, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Plot.ly, BeautifulSoup

Database: SQL, MongoDB, SQLAlchemy, Access

Other: Jira, Azure DevOps, Jupyter, VS Code, GitHub, Git Bash, Advanced Excel, PowerPoint Consulting: Leadership, management, public speaking, presentations, teamwork, problem-solving